<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>umu seminar</title><link>https://umus.github.io/</link><description>universal math umu</description><atom:link href="https://umus.github.io/rss.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2016 06:18:20 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>20161014 UT Math Academic Experience: CUMC Talks</title><link>https://umus.github.io/log/20161014-ut-math-academic-experience-cumc-talks.html</link><dc:creator>umu</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Team,
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am very grateful to all of you who have come today for a series of
fascinating talks by Zachary Karry, Angela Wu and Calder
Morton-Ferguson (by the way, today, Saturday 15, is &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/calder.oakes"&gt;Calder&lt;/a&gt;'s
birthday).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
From &lt;a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/20160330-sphere-packing-solved-in-higher-dimensions/"&gt;the Leech lattice&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://cs.smith.edu/~orourke/TOPP/P57.html#Problem.57"&gt;Hadwider-Nelson&lt;/a&gt; and beyond, there is a trove
of known and unknown results in front of us.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are also happy news: Lola Bradford, Phil Blakey and Jessica
(澄瑾) Liu have expressed their interest in joining our sessions.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I would be happy to hear any reflections, opinions and suggestions you
might have regarding today's talks or sessions in general. For
example, which talk today did you like most?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are also updates on the ut.umu page for linear algebra, where
some resources from George M. Bergman and Terry Tao have been added,
all from the courses taught based on Friedberg et al.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://umus.github.io/log/20161014-ut-math-academic-experience-cumc-talks.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2016 05:56:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>20161014 MAT157/MAT240: CUMC Talks</title><link>https://umus.github.io/log/20161014-mat157mat240-cumc-talks.html</link><dc:creator>umu</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Team,
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am grateful to all of you who have promptly reacted to the quick
questionnaire either in person or by mail.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Out of 6 of those who replied, 6 wish to go or at least &lt;i&gt;check out&lt;/i&gt;
the talks.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am looking forward to seeing you tomorrow at 16:30 in BA2135.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you have any questions, comments or suggestions, please contact me,
it would be extremely refreshing to hear what you think.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Onwards!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
– sasha
&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://umus.github.io/log/20161014-mat157mat240-cumc-talks.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2016 06:28:38 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>20161012 UT MAT157/MAT240: Updates</title><link>https://umus.github.io/log/20161012-ut-mat157mat240-updates.html</link><dc:creator>umu</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Team,
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is a follow-up to &lt;a href="https://umus.github.io/log/20161012-ut-mat157mat240-notices.html"&gt;the announcement made earlier&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The curator of recognized study groups has confirmed that attending
the CUMC talks organized by the Math Union on Friday at 16:30 in
BA2135 counts as an academic experience eligible for CCR.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You can learn more about the talks on the &lt;a href="https://mu.math.toronto.edu/home/blog/2016/10/12/math-union-presents-three-cumc-talks/"&gt;MU website&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Since I am responsible for registering the participants of the study
group attending the academic experience events, I must be present at
either the study session or the CUMC talks to make the session or the
academic experience recognized.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Thus, I would be grateful to hear your opinions on whether you would
prefer to go to the talks or have a study session. To make it easier
for you to reply and save some time for math, please choose one of the
following options and write me an email with its one-letter code:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
(s) Study Session
(t) CUMC Talks
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are several members whose exams overlap with the study session
this Friday. It is fine if you leave a bit early or come a bit late,
provided you still find value in the session or talks.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Moreover, there are three talks, each lasting 20 minutes, and, if most
of us decide to go to the talks, you can come to any one of those to
make it count as an academic experience.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am looking forward to hearing from you as soon as possible.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Onwards!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
– sasha
&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://umus.github.io/log/20161012-ut-mat157mat240-updates.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2016 02:22:27 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>20161012 UT MAT157/MAT240: Notices</title><link>https://umus.github.io/log/20161012-ut-mat157mat240-notices.html</link><dc:creator>umu</dc:creator><description>&lt;script src="https://umus.github.io/assets/scripts/jquery-1.12.2.min.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link rel="stylesheet" href="https://umus.github.io/assets/scripts/katex/katex.min.css"&gt;
&lt;script src="https://umus.github.io/assets/scripts/katex/katex.min.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src="https://umus.github.io/assets/scripts/katex/contrib/auto-render.min.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Team,
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am writing to remind you that this Friday, October 14, we are going
to have our second meeting in B026(seminar room), Bahen, at 16:10.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are several updates this week.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First, Yooveshen Mooroogen, who decided to join our sessions, has
suggested a list of recommended problems from Spivak as given in the
MAT157 syllabus of 2012-2013. The table adapted from the syllabus has
been published on the ut.umu page.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Secondly, ACE of UToronto got back to me about the request of
reserving B026 for our sessions. In order to have such a privilege, we
need to &lt;a href="https://ulife.utoronto.ca/page/view/slug/apply"&gt;recognize our group with ULife&lt;/a&gt; first. The exact procedure will
be investigated in detail after the midterms; there are several
options available. For example, we may try to collaborate with Math
Union. I will contact Angela shortly.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Finally, there are several talks &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/1609525922683111/"&gt;organized by the Math Union&lt;/a&gt; at the
time of our meeting on Friday, from 16:30. The topics include the
following:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Why Some Sequences are More Special than Others&lt;/i&gt; by Calder
Morton-Ferguson
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Chromatic Number of the Plane and the Axiom of Choice&lt;/i&gt; by Angela Wu
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Sphere Packing and the Baffling Properties of the $$E_8$$ and Leech
Lattices&lt;/i&gt; by Zachary Karry
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If there is any interest, I will find out whether this may count as an
academic experience in the context of CCR. If not, it sounds
interesting anyway. Please let me know what you think.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you intend to come earlier than 16:10 on Friday, the schedule on
ACE for B026 shows that the room is going to be vacant after 15:00.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you have any resources relevant to our agenda, for example lecture
outlines from any week, please let me know and I will post them on the
ut.umu page. Please also take a look at the MAT240 course page,
where several bonus problems have been already posted.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am looking forward to seeing you on Friday.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Onwards!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
– sasha
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
renderMathInElement(
document.body,
{
delimiters: [
{left: "$$$", right: "$$$", display: true},
{left: "$$", right: "$$", display: false},
]
}
);
&lt;/script&gt;</description><guid>https://umus.github.io/log/20161012-ut-mat157mat240-notices.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2016 13:01:23 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>UT MAT157: First Session</title><link>https://umus.github.io/log/ut-mat157-first-session.html</link><dc:creator>umu</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Team,
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am grateful to all of you who has come today and made the session
productive despite some element of chaos which is often present in
introductory meetings. And thank you for all the suggestions – they
would definitely help us make our time together worthwhile.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One of the questions raised in the session was about the combination
of training for MAT157 and MAT240 in one session. Everyone is free to
choose any topic or problem to go through during the session, but I do
think it is necessary to have the topic of the main discussion in mind
before each session. My suggestion is to split officially the current
time period in half, and devote one half to analysis and one half to
algebra.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This would allow us to have a clear focus for a set period of time. As
Fiona proposed, it would be great to devote some time in the beginning
of each corresponding session to a quick recap of the week lectures,
since this will give us a headstart with problems, hopefully identify
the gaps in our knowledge and understanding as well as unite our
efforts in a coherent discussion interesting for us all. If you have
the outlines of lectures in any format or want to write them, please
write me an email.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Alan expressed interest in reserving B026 as our base for the future
sessions. I will write to ACE as soon as possible.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Matthew also suggested to create a Facebook group to spread
information. If there is a demand and there are volunteers to look
after the page, I am happy if you get involved with it, but would like
to keep the logs of the sessions, announcements and resources on the
umu website. For those of you who are new, please be aware there is a
Facebook chat in which most of the instantaneous communication takes
place.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you want anything to be posted on the &lt;a href="https://umus.github.io/ut-umu"&gt;ut.umu&lt;/a&gt; page, please feel free
to &lt;a href="https://umus.github.io/contact"&gt;contact&lt;/a&gt; me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Unfortunately, not every person who has participated today has written
me an email. Registering is important if you want to obtain CCR after
attending at least 4 sessions and having 1 academic experience.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The academic experience is supposed to add to our knowledge and
academic skills development, and may involve various activities. We
may book a mathematical (or any other, if there is a demand) &lt;a href="https://onesearch.library.utoronto.ca/consultations"&gt;research
consultation&lt;/a&gt;, visit office hours of the beloved Joe Repka and Eckhard
Meinrenken, a &lt;a href="http://www.artsci.utoronto.ca/current/advising/freeresources"&gt;tutoring centre&lt;/a&gt; or a TA, or we may attend a workshop in
the &lt;a href="http://libcal.library.utoronto.ca/calendar/libraryworkshops/?cid=2020&amp;amp;t=m&amp;amp;d=0000-00-00&amp;amp;cal%255B%255D=2020"&gt;library&lt;/a&gt;. Please write what you think suits you best by email or in the
Facebook chat.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you had not already emailed me but attended the session, I would
be grateful if you could fill the following form to register the
attendance and send it by email from your mail.utoronto.ca address:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First Name
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are there any specific topics you want to go through in the next
session, other than the content of the most recent lectures?
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What rules would you like the group to follow?
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you want your name to appear publicly in the &lt;a href="https://github.com/umus/ut.umu/blob/master/register.csv"&gt;register&lt;/a&gt;? If not,
you may choose a nickname to be used instead. Currently, almost all
names are listed in full. If you want to replace your name with
something else, please drop me an email.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am looking forward to hearing from you.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Onwards!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
—
sasha
&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://umus.github.io/log/ut-mat157-first-session.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2016 22:50:21 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>