<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" version="2.0"><channel><title>umu seminar</title><link>https://umus.github.io/</link><description>universal math umu</description><atom:link type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" href="https://umus.github.io/rss.xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2016 06:48:34 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>20161103 UT MAT157/MAT240: Friday Session Vote Results</title><link>https://umus.github.io/log/20161103-ut-mat157mat240-friday-session-vote-results.html</link><dc:creator>umu</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Team,
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am writing to inform you about the results of the questionnaire.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Out of 7 people whose responses I have received, 6 individuals have
confirmed their availability on Friday, and all of those 6 have chosen
the talks. Thus, the plan is to go to the talks.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Considering the last two days of exciting events in the Fields
Institute, I would be happy to hear the opinions and reflections from
all of you who have managed to join the Bhargavalia. Moreover, if you
are really excited about all the mathemagic you have witnessed and
want to share the oumph with your knowledge-thirsty peers, we can
devote one of the next sessions, perhaps after the analysis midterm,
to your findings.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am looking forwards to seeing you in BA2135 at 4:00 pm on Friday.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Onwards!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
– sasha
&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://umus.github.io/log/20161103-ut-mat157mat240-friday-session-vote-results.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2016 06:31:11 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>20161028 UT MAT157/MAT240: Study Session III and IV</title><link>https://umus.github.io/log/20161028-ut-mat157mat240-study-session-iii-and-iv.html</link><dc:creator>umu</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Team,
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am glad to inform you that last Friday we have had the largest session so far,
with 17 people attending at least the first part of the
session. Welcome to Allan Chang, Agyness Chen, Mrunal Gavali and Shuting
Zhang!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I hope that you have found something useful in this session, and I
hope that you have been inspired to bring your own questions next
time. It was illuminating to see the way Lola, Thomas, Matthew, Fiona
and Alan think while solving problems, and I dare to claim that their
boldness has been integral to the flow of the session.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As Matthew have promptly suggested, this Friday, November 4, MUGS III
talks are going to take place in BA2135 from 16:00 to 18:00. Professor
Burchard, who has interests ranging from geometric problems in
functional analysis, PDE and probability symmetrization to sharp
inequalities scheduling and delay analysis in communication networks,
will be giving a talk on the fruitful topic of symmetries and
reflections, with applications to minimization problems. For example,
we may look at the following question: starting from the north pole,
can we reach any point on the sphere by applying iteratively a finite
set of reflections?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We need to decide on our plan for Friday. If you prefer the talks to
the session, please send me a quick reply with the letter "t" in the
body or the subject of the email. If you, on the other hand, would
rather have a session and skip the talk, please send me the letter
"s". I will write you back with the results as soon as I get a
representative number of replies. Note that the talks will be counted
as an academic experience for the MAT240 study group (last time the
talks were counted as an academic experience for MAT157), which is one
of the requirements for getting CCR by the end of the term.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a side note, if you have a github account and wish to contribute
any notes, handouts or any other material to the &lt;a href="https://github.com/umus/ut.umu"&gt;ut.umu repository&lt;/a&gt;,
please drop me an email with your account name.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I wish you a productive week and look forward to hearing from you soon.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Onwards!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
– sasha
&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://umus.github.io/log/20161028-ut-mat157mat240-study-session-iii-and-iv.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2016 15:40:06 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>20161028 UT MAT157/MAT240 Study Session III</title><link>https://umus.github.io/log/20161028-ut-mat157mat240-study-session-iii.html</link><dc:creator>umu</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Team,
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I hope you have had a good night sleep so that you are ready for yet
another wonderful and productive Friday.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are amazing news – Shuting Zhang and Allan Chang have expressed
their interest in our sessions, and I hope they will be able to come
to today at 16:10, B026 (seminar room) in Bahen.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As always, it would be beneficial for the entire group if you could
think about questions you wish to ask during the session, any problems
you are curious about or any exciting mathematical adventures you have
been involved with that you can share with us.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Today, similarly to the last time, the preliminary plan is to split
the session into two parts, one devoted to analysis and one to linear
algebra, but there is room for any suggestions you might have.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have also added some information to the ut.umu page about CCR that
you can receive by attending the sessions.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am looking forward to seeing you soon.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Onwards!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
– sasha
&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://umus.github.io/log/20161028-ut-mat157mat240-study-session-iii.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2016 09:32:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>20161021 UT MAT157/MAT240: Preparation for Study Session III</title><link>https://umus.github.io/log/20161021-ut-mat157mat240-preparation-for-study-session-iii.html</link><dc:creator>umu</dc:creator><description>&lt;script src="https://umus.github.io/assets/scripts/jquery-1.12.2.min.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link rel="stylesheet" href="https://umus.github.io/assets/scripts/katex/katex.min.css"&gt;
&lt;script src="https://umus.github.io/assets/scripts/katex/katex.min.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src="https://umus.github.io/assets/scripts/katex/contrib/auto-render.min.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Team,
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am extremely grateful to all of you who have come today and made the
session productive.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It has been a pleasure to study in the environment full of initiative
and support. Thanks to all of you who have asked questions, dared to
be confused and took a risk of showing what and how they think in
front of a dozen of peers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I hope you have found something useful in the session today. If not,
it would be great to hear what might have been done better. And the
suggestions of interesting topics or problems you may wish to add to
the agenda in the future are hugely welcomed!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Following the discussion of the Nested Interval Theorem, which turns
out to be a consequence of &lt;a href="http://mathworld.wolfram.com/CantorsIntersectionTheorem.html"&gt;Cantor's Intersection Theorem&lt;/a&gt;, here is the
problem from Spivak with which the Intermediate Value Theorem can be
proven differently from how it has been done in class:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Suppose $$f$$ is continuous on $$[a, b]$$ and $$f(a) &amp;lt; 0 &amp;lt; f(b)$$.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then either $$f(\frac{a + b}{2}) = 0$$,
or $$f$$ has different signs at the end points of $$[a, \frac{a+b}{2}]$$,
or $$f$$ has different signs at the end points of $$[\frac{a + b}{2}, b]$$.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If $$f(\frac{a + b}{2}) \neq 0$$, let $$I_1$$ be one of the two
intervals on which $$f$$ changes sign. Now bisect $$I_1$$. Either $$f$$
is $$0$$ at the midpoint, or $$f$$ changes sign on one of the two
intervals. Let $$I_2$$ be such an interval. Continue in this way, to
define $$I_n$$ for each $$n$$ (unless $$f$$ is $$0$$ at some
midpoint). Use the Nested Interval Theorem to find a point $$x$$ where
$$f(x) = 0$$.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I hope you have a refreshing weekend.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Onwards!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
– sasha
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
renderMathInElement(
document.body,
{
delimiters: [
{left: "$$$", right: "$$$", display: true},
{left: "$$", right: "$$", display: false},
]
}
);
&lt;/script&gt;</description><guid>https://umus.github.io/log/20161021-ut-mat157mat240-preparation-for-study-session-iii.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2016 23:25:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>20161021 UT MAT157/MAT240: Study Session II</title><link>https://umus.github.io/log/20161021-ut-mat157mat240-study-session-ii.html</link><dc:creator>umu</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Team,
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am writing to remind you that we are planning to meet today at 16:10
in B026 (seminar room), Bahen.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As we have decided earlier, the session is going to be split into two,
one devoted to LA, and one to RA.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I would be extremely grateful if in the meantime you could think about
any questions you want to ask for the common discussion, any topics
you wish to be covered, and whether there is any material you are
willing to tell the group about.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For example, it would be exciting to learn from those of you who are
going through (have finished?) Baby Rudin and have studied Chapters
I-IV how our dear Walter treats continuity through metric spaces,
provided it is possible to compact the highly alluring lecture into
our time limits. Of course, it would be great to hear about any other
topic you find useful.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are also updates to the MAT157 Resources section of the ut.umu
page, where the Companion Notes to PMA by Professor Evelyn Silvia have
been added.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am looking forward to seeing you today.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Good luck to all of you who have a midterm today.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Onwards!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
– sasha
&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://umus.github.io/log/20161021-ut-mat157mat240-study-session-ii.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2016 09:50:39 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>20161018 UT MAT240: Past Midterms</title><link>https://umus.github.io/log/20161018-ut-mat240-past-midterms.html</link><dc:creator>umu</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Team,
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I hope most of you plan or in the progress of a good night sleep.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I certainly do.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This email is just to notify you that I have added 4 past MAT240
midterms for morning preparation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Moreover, two sincere and lively comments have been added to the
Comments section at the end of the page.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Good night, and good luck.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Onwards!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
– sasha
&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://umus.github.io/log/20161018-ut-mat240-past-midterms.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2016 04:10:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>20161017 UT MAT240: 20161018 Midterm Resources</title><link>https://umus.github.io/log/20161018-ut-mat240-midterm-resources.html</link><dc:creator>umu</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Team,
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I hope you have had a productive and refreshing weekend, so
that tomorrow you get to grips and fully engage with the
midterm exam.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A table with the problems from Friedberg et al, recommended
by Professor Meinrenken since the beginning of the term, is
now up on the &lt;a href="https://umus.github.io/ut-umu.html#sec-1-2-1"&gt;ut.umu page&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You may also find the link to Terry Tao's LA course webpage
in the same section, where sample and actual midterms with
solutions are given.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I wish you good luck and lucid state of mind tomorrow.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Onwards!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
– sasha
&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://umus.github.io/log/20161018-ut-mat240-midterm-resources.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2016 23:52:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>20161014 UT Math Academic Experience: CUMC Talks</title><link>https://umus.github.io/log/20161014-ut-math-academic-experience-cumc-talks.html</link><dc:creator>umu</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Team,
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am very grateful to all of you who have come today for a series of
fascinating talks by Zachary Karry, Angela Wu and Calder
Morton-Ferguson (by the way, today, Saturday 15, is &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/calder.oakes"&gt;Calder&lt;/a&gt;'s
birthday).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
From &lt;a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/20160330-sphere-packing-solved-in-higher-dimensions/"&gt;the Leech lattice&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://cs.smith.edu/~orourke/TOPP/P57.html#Problem.57"&gt;Hadwider-Nelson&lt;/a&gt; and beyond, there is a trove
of known and unknown results awaiting our attention.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are also happy news: Lola Bradford, Phil Blakey and Jessica
(澄瑾) Liu have expressed their interest in joining our sessions.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I would be happy to hear any reflections, opinions and suggestions you
might have regarding today's talks or sessions in general. For
example, which talk today did you like most?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are also updates on the ut.umu page for linear algebra, where
some resources from George M. Bergman and Terry Tao have been added,
all from the courses taught based on Friedberg et al.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I wish you a restful and productive weekend.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Onwards!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
– sasha
&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://umus.github.io/log/20161014-ut-math-academic-experience-cumc-talks.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2016 05:56:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>20161014 UT MAT157/MAT240: CUMC Talks</title><link>https://umus.github.io/log/20161014-mat157mat240-cumc-talks.html</link><dc:creator>umu</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Team,
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am grateful to all of you who have promptly reacted to the quick
questionnaire either in person or by mail.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Out of 6 of those who replied, 6 wish to go or at least &lt;i&gt;check out&lt;/i&gt;
the talks.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am looking forward to seeing you tomorrow at 16:30 in BA2135.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you have any questions, comments or suggestions, please contact me,
it would be extremely refreshing to hear what you think.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Onwards!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
– sasha
&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://umus.github.io/log/20161014-mat157mat240-cumc-talks.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2016 06:28:38 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>20161012 UT MAT157/MAT240: Updates</title><link>https://umus.github.io/log/20161012-ut-mat157mat240-updates.html</link><dc:creator>umu</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Team,
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is a follow-up to &lt;a href="https://umus.github.io/log/20161012-ut-mat157mat240-notices.html"&gt;the announcement made earlier&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The curator of recognized study groups has confirmed that attending
the CUMC talks organized by the Math Union on Friday at 16:30 in
BA2135 counts as an academic experience eligible for CCR.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You can learn more about the talks on the &lt;a href="https://mu.math.toronto.edu/home/blog/2016/10/12/math-union-presents-three-cumc-talks/"&gt;MU website&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Since I am responsible for registering the participants of the study
group attending the academic experience events, I must be present at
either the study session or the CUMC talks to make the session or the
academic experience recognized.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Thus, I would be grateful to hear your opinions on whether you would
prefer to go to the talks or have a study session. To make it easier
for you to reply and save some time for math, please choose one of the
following options and write me an email with its one-letter code:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
(s) Study Session
(t) CUMC Talks
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are several members whose exams overlap with the study session
this Friday. It is fine if you leave a bit early or come a bit late,
provided you still find value in the session or talks.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Moreover, there are three talks, each lasting 20 minutes, and, if most
of us decide to go to the talks, you can come to any one of those to
make it count as an academic experience.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am looking forward to hearing from you as soon as possible.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Onwards!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
– sasha
&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://umus.github.io/log/20161012-ut-mat157mat240-updates.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2016 02:22:27 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>